Finding Aid for the Collection of Research Materials Related to Linguistic-Psychological Studies of Genie (pseudonym), 1895-2003, 1970-2003 LSC.0800
UCLA Library Special Collections
- 2. Conference papers, essays and reports, 1968-1983
  - Kent, James T. / Eight months in the hospital, 1972 September 1-8 (Box 50, Folder 16)
    Prepared for presentation at the 80th Annual Convention of the American Psychological Association.
  - Krashen, Stephen / [Untitled working paper], ca. 1972 March (Box 50, Folder 17)
  - Krashen, Stephen, et al / Language lateralization in a case of psychosocial deprivation, ca. 1973 (Box 50, Folder 18)
  - Krashen, Stephen, et al / Neurolinguistic investigation of language acquisition in the case of an isolated child, 1972 December (Box 50, Folder 19)
    Prepared for presentation at the winter meeting of the Linguistic Society of America, Atlanta, Georgia.
  - Language development beyond the 'critical age', ca. 1971 (Box 50, Folder 20)
    Edited draft. Also includes photocopies of material entitled "Results of Comprehension Tests."
  - Language development beyond the 'critical age', ca. 1971 (Box 84, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript--Genie's history, ca. 1975 (Box 50, Folder 21)
    Handwritten draft by David Rigler.
  - Material regarding conference at Université Laval, Québec, Canada, 1975 June 18-1976 April 1 (Box 50, Folder 22)
    Regarding David Rigler's conference regarding psycho-social causes of the battered childhood syndrome.
  - Material regarding conference at Université Laval, Québec, Canada, 1975 June 18-1976 April 1 (Box 85, Folder 7)
  - Outline for slide presentation, 1972 January 20 (Box 50, Folder 23)
  - Paper discussing the linguistic development of Genie, ca. 1973 (Box 50, Folder 24)
    No title or author.
  - Program proposal submission, 1976 April 22 (Box 50, Folder 25)
    Title: An abused child's percept of family: a case study
  - Richardson, Toni / Sign language as a means of communication for the institutionalized mentally retarded, 1974 June (Box 50, Folder 26)
    Staff member of the Southbury Training School, Neurologically Impaired Program.
  - Rigler, David / Adolescence and hypnotherapy, 1983 November 30 (Box 50, Folder 27)
    Presented at International Congress on Ericksonian Approaches to Hypnosis and Psychotherapy, Phoenix, AZ.
  - Rigler, David / Case of Genie: primary language learning in adolescence with extreme psychosocial deprivation: special problems relating to evaluation of cognition, 1972 November 18-20 (Box 50, Folder 28)
    Prepared for presentation at the Annual Convention of the American Speech and Hearing Association, San Francisco, California
  - Rigler, David / Problems associated with evaluation and amelioration of prolonged deprivation, 1973 March 30 (Box 50, Folder 29)
    Presented as part of a symposium entitled Sensory and Social Deprivation: Conceptual and Clinical Perspectives. Society for Research in Child Development, Biennial Meeting, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
  - Rigler, David / Prolonged deprivation: evaluation and amelioration, 1973 October 20 (Box 50, Folder 30)
    Presented as part of a symposium entitled: Sensory and Social Deprivation: Conceptual and Clinical Perspectives
  - Rigler, David and Marilyn Rigler / Attenuation of severe phobia in a historic case of extreme psychosocial deprivation, 1972 January 12; undated (Box 50, Folder 31)
    Paper draft and notes on Genie's cat and dog phobias.
  - Rigler, David and Marilyn Rigler / Attenuation of severe phobia in a historic case of extreme psychosocial deprivation, 1972 (Box 50, Folder 32)
    Abstract for 20th International Congress of Psychology in Tokyo, Japan.
  - Rigler, David and Marilyn Rigler / Persistent Effects of Early Experience, 1975 April 12 (Box 50, Folder 33)
    Paper presented at Society for Research in Child Development, Denver, Colorado.
  - Rigler, David, et al / Psychobiological study of an isolated thirteen-year-old girl, 1971 September 30 (Box 84, Folder 1)
    Final report of a study undertaken under provisions of a negotiated contract, HSM-42-71-31, with the National Institute of Mental Health, Health Services and Mental Health Administration, Department of Health, Education and Welfare.
  - Rigler, David, et al / Overview of Genie's developing language, ca. 1974 September (Box 84, Folder 2)
    Prepared for presentation at Sign Language and Neurolinguistics conference, Rochester, New York, September 24- 25.
  - Rigler, Marilyn / Adventure: at home with Genie, 1972 September 1-8 (Box 84, Folder 3)
    Abstract and paper presented at the 80th Annual American Psychological Association Convention, Honolulu, Hawaii. in a symposium, "Extreme Psychosocial Deprivation: The Case of Genie," David Rigler, Ph.D., Chairman.
  - Rigler, Marilyn / Adventure: at home with Genie, 1972 November 18-20 (Box 84, Folder 4)
    Prepared for presentation at the Annual Convention of the American Speech and Hearing Association, San Francisco, California.
  - Shurley, Jay / Social deprivation and social isolation: a review and attempt at integration, 1968 February 29 (Box 84, Folder 5)
  - Shurley, Jay T. / Sleep EEG patterns in a fourteen-year-old girl with severe development retardation, 1972 January 21 (Box 84, Folder 6)
    One-page abstract.
  - Shurley, Jay T. and Kirmach Natani / Sleep EEG patterns in a fourteen-year-old girl with severe developmental retardation, 1972 September (Box 84, Folder 7)
    Prepared for presentation at the American Psychological Association Annual Convention, Honolulu, Hawaii, September 1-8, 1972. Includes formal paper and one-page synopsis of findings.
  - Stanford University School of Medicine Fifth Child Language Research Forum--Various material, 1973 January 19-1973 May 9 (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Transcript of symposium "Extreme Psychosocial Deprivation: The Case of Genie", 1972 September 6 (Box 84, Folder 8)
    Held during the 80th Annual American Psychological Association Convention, Honolulu, Hawaii.
  - Various material for International Congress of Psychology, Tokyo, Japan, 1972 January 12 (Box 84, Folder 9)
    Correspondence, instructions for submitting manuscript.
  - Various material for SRCD conference, 1973 March 8-1973 March 30 (Box 84, Folder 10)
    For presentation as part of a symposium entitled Sensory and Social Deprivation: Conceptual and Clinical Perspectives. Society for Research in Child Development. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
  - Wilson, Paula Starks / Sign language as a means of communication for the mentally retarded, ca. 1973 (Box 84, Folder 11)
    Also includes directory of programs and people involved in the use of sign language with the mentally retarded
  - World Federation for Mental Health symposium material, 1972 August 1-November 29 (Box 84, Folder 12)
- 3. Funding, 1970-1976
  The series is comprised of correspondence, financial paperwork, grant applications, and other materials regarding funding needs and sources for the study. Some of these materials, due to privacy concerns, may be inaccessible to researchers. Please consult the Manuscripts Librarian in advance so that access arrangements can be made as appropriate.
  Arranged in subseries A-C as follows:
  3A. Childrens Hospital of Los Angeles
  3B. Grant Foundation
  3C. National Institute of Mental Health.
  - 3A. Childrens Hospital Los Angeles, 1970-1976
    This subseries consists mainly of correspondence and budget expenditure paperwork, but also includes a small amount of miscellaneous material.
    - Advance request or expense report, 1974 November 13 (Box 51, Folder 2)
      Travel expenses for trip to San Diego Childrens Hospital Speech and Hearing Center.
    - Correspondence--Beaty, William T. to David Rigler, 1974 January 10 (Box 51, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence--Diogerardi, Sarah to David Rigler, 1973 August 16 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence--Duque, Mrs. Gabriel C. to George R. Olincy, Andrew Norman Foundation, 1973 November 30 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence--Fromkin, Victoria to David Rigler, 1976 February 11 (Box 51, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence--Hansen, Howard, 1973 January 26 (Box 51, Folder 7)
      Memorandum to George Donnell regarding re-application.
    - Correspondence--Letters to and from Alan Bell of National Science Foundation, 1975 March 21; 1975 April 9 (Box 51, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David to Ralph Guillon, 1971 October 13 (Box 51, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David to Robert Ward, 1971 November 2 (Box 51, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David. Solicitation letters, 1973 November 14-1973 December 18 (Box 51, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David to Gabriel C. Duque, Board of Directors, Childrens Hospital of Los Angeles, 1973 November 29 (Box 51, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence--Tarjan, George to David Rigler, 1974 January 25 (Box 51, Folder 13)
    - Fund 7841--Budget and Expenditures, 1971-1972 (Box 51, Folder 14)
    - Fund 7841--Budget and Expenditures, 1972-1973 (Box 51, Folder 15)
    - Fund 7907--Equipment charges, 1972 February 7 (Box 51, Folder 16)
    - Fund 7907--Expenditures and invoices, 1970 November 25-1971 August (Box 51, Folder 17)
    - Fund 7907--Tentative report, 1972 January 26 (Box 51, Folder 18)
    - Fund 7908--Expenditures and invoices, 1971 July 19-1971 October (Box 51, Folder 19)
    - Fund 80436--Budget and expenditures, 1975 January 10-1975 December (Box 51, Folder 20)
      Material taken from binder. Includes budget and expense reports for the final year of grant.
    - Fund 80463--Various correspondence and memos concerning the grant, 1971 May 3-1975 February 6 (Box 52, Folder 1)
    - Material regarding funding sources for Genie, 1970 November (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Material regarding Genie's funding needs, 1970 December 12-1972 February 16 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - 3B. Grant Foundation, 1970-1971
    This subseries consists entirely of correspondence.
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David to Philip Sapir, 1970 December 8-1973 November 14 (Box 52, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence--Russell, Lynn to David Rigler, 1971 November 30 (Box 52, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence--Sapir, Philip to David Rigler, 1971 July-1976 August 12 (Box 52, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence--Sapir, Philip to Howard Hansen, 1970 December 17 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence--Sapir, Philip to Harold P. Dean, 1971 January 8 (Box 52, Folder 8)
  - 3C. National Institute of Mental Health, 1970-1976
    This subseries consists of the primary grant applications of 1971-1974, correspondence, budgetary paperwork, and other assorted material.
    - Correspondence--Author unknown, ca. 1973 October (Box 52, Folder 9)
      Draft correspondence to David Rigler regarding discussion with Dr. E. Wayne Herron regarding grant renewal request.
    - Correspondence--Fowler, [W.F.?] to David Rigler, 1971 February 19 (Box 52, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence--Hansen, Howard, ca. 1971 September (Box 52, Folder 11)
      Regarding new position available via the NIMH research contract.
    - Correspondence--Herron, E. Wayne to David Rigler, 1973 May 25; 1974 December 12 (Box 52, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence--HSM-42-71-31, 1971 March 29-1971 September 9 (Box 52, Folder 13)
      Various incoming and outgoing correspondence.
    - Correspondence--Miller, John C. to David Rigler, 1976 March 19 (Box 52, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence--Pearl, David to David Rigler, 1974 December 6 (Box 52, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David to Louis A. Wienckowski, 1970 December 3; 1971 February 22 (Box 52, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David to E. Wayne Herron, 1973 March 28-1974 December 17 (Box 52, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David, ca. 1973 October (Box 52, Folder 18)
      Draft of letter to Dr. E. Wayne Herron regarding follow-up to recent site visit for the evaluation of the grant renewal request.
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David to David Pearl, 1971 March 22-1974 May 8 (Box 52, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David to Harry B. Neustein, 1976 March 19 (Box 52, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David to Alvin Goins, 1973 April 27 (Box 52, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence--Rigler, David to the National Institute of Health, 1974 May 29 (Box 52, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence--Woodson, JoAnn to David Rigler, 1975 January 13 (Box 52, Folder 23)
    - Ephemera--General information for grant applicants, ca. 1973 (Box 52, Folder 24)
    - Grant application--Developmental consequence of extreme social isolation, 1971 June 11 (Box 52, Folder 25)
    - Grant application--Developmental consequence of extreme social isolation, 1972 August 3 (Box 52, Folder 26)
    - Grant application--Developmental consequence of extreme social isolation, 1973 January 26 (Box 52, Folder 27)
    - Grant application--Developmental consequence of extreme social isolation, 1974 May 30 (Box 52, Folder 28)
    - MH-21191--Appendix to renewal grant application (copy no. 20), and photographs, ca. 1973 (Box 52, Folder 29)
      Includes two photographs of Genie and major papers presented at conferences.
    - MH-21191--Application for continuation grant, 1972 August 3 (Box 52, Folder 30)
    - MH-21191--Budget for three-month extension, 1973 October-December (Box 53, Folder 1)
    - MH-21191--Budget material related to grant, 1971 October 14-1972 August 2 (Box 53, Folder 2)
    - MH-21191--Check sheet for submitting application for research grants, ca. 1973 (Box 53, Folder 3)
    - MH-21191--Check sheet for submitting application for research grant, 1974 May 30 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    - MH-21191--Detailed budget for first 12-month period, 1970 December 15 (Box 53, Folder 5)
    - MH-21191--Expenditures for the report period, 1973 January 7 (Box 53, Folder 6)
    - MH-21191--Monthly budget and expense reports, 1974 January-December (Box 53, Folder 7)
    - MH-21191--Various correspondence and material, 1971 February 22-1978 April 11 (Box 53, Folder 8)
    - MH-21191--Various material, 1971 February 22-1978 February 28 (Box 53, Folder 9)
    - MH-21191--Various material related to grant, 1971 May 20-1972 February 8 (Box 53, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous material on expenditures, 1971 May-1971 July 9 (Box 53, Folder 11)
    - Negotiated contract, ca. 1971 (Box 53, Folder 12)
    - Notes for renewal of application of 'Genie grant', ca. 1973 January (Box 53, Folder 13)
    - David Rigler's notes from phone call with Daniel Pearl regarding grant proposal, ca. 1971 (Box 53, Folder 14)
    - Notice of grant awarded, 1974 June 1 (Box 53, Folder 15)
    - Report of research grant expenditures, 1976 June 4 (Box 53, Folder 16)
    - Request to continue the study of the Genie's development, ca. 1973 April (Box 53, Folder 17)
      Includes comprehensive progress report and bibliographic references.
    - Rigler, David. Draft letter to L. Alan Sroufe, ca. 1973 (Box 53, Folder 18)
    - Supplementary information for personnel costs requested, 1972 February 23 (Box 53, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence and grant applications, 1971-1974 (Box 53, Folder 20)
      Correspondence and grant applications.
    - Various material gathered for site visit June 18, 1973, 1971-1973 (Box 53, Folder 21)
- 4. Guardianship, 1970-1978
  This series is comprised of correspondence, items related to Genie's education, legal paperwork regarding Genie's foster care, and other miscellaneous material. Some of these materials, due to privacy concerns, may be inaccessible to researchers. Please consult the Manuscripts Librarian in advance so that access arrangements can be made as appropriate.
  Subseries subseries A-D as follows:
  4A. Correspondence
  4B. Education
  4C. Legal materials
  4D. Miscellaneous.
  - 4A. Correspondence, 1971-1978
    This subseries includes correspondence regarding various aspects of David and Marilyn Rigler's roles as Genie's foster parents, including communication with schools and Los Angeles social service departments. Also includes items concerning Genie's placement after she left the Rigler's home.
    - Butler, Jean to David Rigler regarding need for a meeting with the Los Angeles District, 1971 March 7 (Box 53, Folder 22)
    - Arredondo, David to John Miner, 1977 February 22 (Box 53, Folder 23)
    - Cohen, Seymour R. re. Genie's medical exam, 1971 November 1 (Box 53, Folder 24)
    - County of Los Angeles Department of Public Social Services. Permission to travel with the Riglers, 1973 April 12; 1974 April 1 (Box 53, Folder 25)
    - Curtiss, Susan and Jeni E. Yamada to John Miner regarding Genie's placement, 1978 January 6 (Box 84, Folder 13)
    - Curtiss, Susan and Jeni E. Yamada to John Miner regarding Genie's placement, 1978 January 6 (Box 53, Folder 26)
    - Curtiss, Susan R. draft letter to Los Angeles Mental Health Center, 1977 August 23 (Box 84, Folder 14)
    - Curtiss, Susan R. draft letter to Los Angeles Mental Health Center, 1977 August 23 (Box 53, Folder 27)
    - Greenan, Thomas F. to David Rigler re: placement in Crockett home, 1977 May 18 (Box 84, Folder 15)
    - Greenan, Thomas F. to David Rigler, re. placement in the Crockett home., 1977 May 18 (Box 53, Folder 28)
    - Lambert, Earl to David Rigler, 1978 November 28 (Box 53, Folder 29)
    - Light, Sally to the Riglers, re. foster home license, 1971 September 27 (Box 53, Folder 30)
    - Longenecker, Ethel to the Riglers, 1973 August 1 (Box 53, Folder 31)
    - Rigler, David to Dr. Ernest P. Willenberg, Los Angeles Unified School District, 1971 May 7 (Box 53, Folder 32)
    - Rigler, David to Jean Butler, 1971 August 6 (Box 84, Folder 16)
    - Rigler, David to Jean Butler, 1971 August 6-7 (Box 53, Folder 33)
    - Rigler, David. Draft memorandum to Mr. Carson re: Butler letter to Mr. Galloway, 1971 October 6 (Box 84, Folder 17)
    - Rigler, David. Draft memorandum to Mr. Carson regarding Jean Butler's letter to Mr. Galloway, 1971 October 6 (Box 53, Folder 34)
    - Rigler, David. Memorandum to Dr. George Donnell, 1971 December 11 (Box 53, Folder 35)
      Regarding Jean Butler's allegations and behavior in regards to Genie.
    - Rigler, David to John Miner, 1972-1975; 1977 (Box 53, Folder 36)
    - Rigler, David to Stanley Wauchope, Principal, Diane Leichman School, 1974 October 4 (Box 53, Folder 37)
    - Rigler, David to Gloria Shepard. Summary of Genie's history, 1975 June 4 (Box 53, Folder 38)
    - Rigler, David to Saundra Thexton, Bureau of Social Services, 1975 June 5 (Box 54, Folder 1)
    - Rigler, David to James Hurst, Principal, Lincoln School, 1975 June 5 (Box 54, Folder 2)
    - Various correspondence and legal documents related to Genie's guardianship, 1977 January 3-1978 November 28 (Box 54, Folder 3)
    - Wiley, Irene. Letters to David Rigler and Marilyn Rigler describing Susan's overnight visits., 1973 December 31; 1974 January 26 (Box 54, Folder 4)
  - 4B. Education, 1970-1977
    Subseries is comprised of school progress reports, pedagogical material from the Los Angeles Unified School District, a small amount of correspondence, and other ephemera and miscellaneous material.
    - Authorization for exchange of medical, psychological, and education information between school and David Rigler, 1975 June 2 (Box 54, Folder 5)
      Signed by Irene Wiley.
    - Diane S. Leichman School--Correspondence, 1975 June 12 (Box 54, Folder 6)
      Letter regarding Genie leaving school.
    - Diane S. Leichman School--Correspondence, 1974 June 11; 1974 October 4 (Box 54, Folder 7)
      Regarding placement of Genie at the school and her psychological testing.
    - Diane S. Leichman School--Notes and progress reports, 1974 May 2; 1975 June 12-13 (Box 54, Folder 8)
    - Diane S. Leichman School--Progress report card for Genie, 1975 January 24 (Box 54, Folder 9)
    - Immaculate Heart College--Progress report, 1973 February 15 (Box 54, Folder 10)
    - Lincoln School--Graduation program, 1976 [June?] (Box 54, Folder 11)
    - Lincoln School--Various paperwork, 1976-1977 (Box 54, Folder 12)
      School notices and rules, Genie's medical certification, immunization history and consent, and pupil summary record.
    - Los Angeles Unified School District--Miscellaneous material, 1971-1973 (Box 84, Folder 18)
    - Los Angeles Unified School District--Miscellaneous material, 1971-1973; 1976 June 20 (Box 54, Folder 13)
      Correspondence, notes, and other material.
    - Los Angeles Unified School District--Sample material, 1970 December 14 (Box 54, Folder 14)
      Illustrates a systematic educational program for a child who needs rehabilitation.
    - Sophia T. Salvin School--Culmination ceremonies material, 1974 June 19 (Box 54, Folder 15)
      Includes program enclosed in original art work [Genie's ?] and copy of certificate of completion.
    - Sophia T. Salvin School--Individual examination report for Genie, 1973 January 15 (Box 54, Folder 16)
    - Sophia T. Salvin School--Progress report cards and parent conference reports, 1973 June 14; 1974 June 20 (Box 54, Folder 17)
    - Sophia T. Salvin School--Progress reports, 1973 June 14, 1974 February 1 (Box 54, Folder 18)
  - 4C. Legal, 1970-1978
    Subseries consists of social worker reports, the Rigler's foster care paperwork, notices of court hearings, and material from John Miner, Genie's state-appointed attorney and advocate.
    - Butler, Jean / Facts regarding the Susan Wiley case from the daily notes and memory of Jean O. Butler, 1971 September 14 (Box 54, Folder 19)
    - Case number 408818--Notice of hearing, 1976 April 30 (Box 54, Folder 20)
    - Case number 408818--Notices of hearings and disposition proceedings, 1973 September 7-1975 June 13 (Box 54, Folder 21)
    - Case number P 581851--Affidavit of attending physician, 1972 March 30 (Box 54, Folder 22)
    - Case number P 581851--Declaration of David Rigler, 1978 August 23 (Box 84, Folder 19)
    - Case number P 581851--Declaration of David Rigler, 1978 August 23 (Box 54, Folder 23)
    - Case number P 581851--Subpoena for David Rigler, 1978 September 1 (Box 54, Folder 24)
    - Children's Services worker's report, 1975 June 13 (Box 54, Folder 25)
    - Children's Services worker's report, 1975 June 13 (Box 54, Folder 26)
    - Department of Mental Hygiene licenses for the Rigler home, 1972 January 15-1975 December 10 (Box 84, Folder 20)
    - Department of Mental Hygiene licenses for the Rigler home, 1972 January 15-1975 December 10 (Box 54, Folder 27)
    - Department of Public Social Services material, 1971 May 17-1972 October 16 (Box 54, Folder 28)
      Incoming and outgoing correspondence and hand written notes regarding costs for permanent placement
    - Foster parent paperwork, 1971 September 21-1972 March 24 (Box 54, Folder 29)
    - Foster Care Payment Voucher material, nd. (Box 84, Folder 21)
    - Foster care payment voucher material, 1973 June 1-1975 March 1 (Box 54, Folder 30)
    - Foster care paperwork, 1974 September 30 (Box 54, Folder 31)
    - Miner, John--Various material, 1972 September 1-1978 September 18 (Box 54, Folder 32)
      Includes power of attorney and other authorizations.
    - Miner, John--Genie file, 1978 March-1979 March (Box 54, Folder 33)
      Contains correspondence and extensive notes regarding numerous foster homes after Genie left Rigler's.
    - Notice of hearing in juvenile court of Los Angeles, 1972 October 10 (Box 54, Folder 34)
    - Notice of hearing in juvenile court of Los Angeles, 1975 May 29 (Box 54, Folder 35)
    - Omanksy, Susan--handwritten note, ca. 1974 October 24 (Box 54, Folder 36)
    - Social worker's report, 1970 November 5 (Box 54, Folder 37)
      Original recommendation to remove Genie from parents and made a dependent child of the court.
  - 4D. Miscellaneous, 1971-1978
    Subseries consists of a variety of material including items related to Jean Butler's involvement in Genie's foster care placement, various notes by David Rigler, Department of Social Services paperwork, and other miscellaneous material.